Finding Aid for Burton L. Baker Papers 1950-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Burton L. Baker Papers 1950-1978
Baker, Burton L. (Burton Lowell), 1912-1978.
2.5 linear feet
Professor of anatomy in the University of Michigan Medical School, 1941-1978. Correspondence and other materials relating to his research activities, the publication of books and articles, and the teaching of anatomy.
8566 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Burton L. Baker (donor no. 6319 ) and came to the library in 1979.
The collection is open for research.
Burton Lowell Baker was born April 2, 1912 in Fife Lake, Michigan. He received his initial college education at Kalamazoo College (A.B., 1933). Afterward he specialized in anatomical studies at Kansas State College (M.S., 1935) and Columbia University (Ph.D., 1941).
Baker began his teaching career at Columbia, but taught there only briefly. Most of his teaching was done at the University of Michigan. He came to Ann Arbor as an instructor of anatomy in 1941. In 1945 he was named an assistant professor, in 1947 an associate professor, and in 1952 he became a full professor.
Baker was constantly involved in research. Initially he was interested in cytology and the function of the parathyroid and adrenal glands, as well as the placenta. Later he investigated the local action of adrenocortical steroids and hormonal regulation of the gastrointestinal tract. His last projects concentrated upon the functional cytology of the pituitary gland and its regulation by the brain. His research led to the publication of over 110 papers.
Baker served on a number of committees. Within the university he sat on various committees specializing in medical areas as well as committees dealing with broader subjects such as the Rackham School of Graduate Studies executive board; Advisory Committee on Appointments, Promotions and Titles in the Medical School; and the Medical School Executive Committee. Outside the university Baker served on important committees for both the American Cancer Society and the National Institute of Health.
Baker was active in the university and academic communities when he died on October 14, 1978.
The papers which survive Dr. Baker reflect only the latter part of his life, primarily 1970 to 1978. They are arranged in a single Alphabetical Subject File. Most of the material is of a routine nature. Those research notes which remain are primarily drafts of published articles, often with a copy of the article and correspondence with the publisher filed with the research. The collection does include files from Dr. Burton's class in anatomy.
Subjects:
Anatomy.; Baker, Burton L. (Burton Lowell), 1912-1978.; Medicine--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
- Alphabetical File
  - American Journal of Anatomy
    - General correspondence 1970-1975 (Box 1)
    - Clark, Sam L. Jr. 1968-1975 (Box 1)
    - P.E. Smith Memorial volume 1972 (Box 1)
  - Anatomy Department 1965-1977 (Box 1)
  - Baker, B.L., biographical (Box 1)
  - Cancer Planning
    - NCI trip 1973 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Committee on Anatomical Nomenclature 1972-1975, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Faculty Award Committee 1978 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree Committee 1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Personal 1967-1978 (Box 1)
    - Positions (applications to) 1959-1975 (Box 1)
    - University correspondence 1968-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Research
      - National Institute of Health 1960-1976, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - General 1958-1978, 10 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous 1973-1978, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Editorial Boards and Manuscripts submitted
    - Site visits made (Box 2)
    - Journal of Histochemistry and Cytochemistry (Box 2)
    - Endocrinology (Box 2)
    - "Effect of Treatment with Growth Hormone on Somatostutin in the Median Eminence of Hypophysectomized Rats" (Box 2)
    - "Immunocytochemical Analysis of Cells in the Pars Tuberalis of the Rat Hypophis with Antisera to Hormones of the Pars distalis" (Box 2)
    - "Distribution of Growth Hormone Release Inhibiting Hormone (Somatostatin) in the Rat Brain as Observed with Immunocytochemistry" (Box 2)
  - Literature
    - Ciba (Box 2)
    - Dermody (Box 2)
    - Ingle Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Merck (Box 2)
    - Nisvender, Gordon D. (Box 2)
    - Oral Contraceptives (Box 2)
    - Radioautography (Box 2)
    - Rat colony (Box 2)
    - Schering Corporation (Box 2)
    - Searle (Box 2)
    - Upjohn (Box 2)
  - Medical School
    - Drummond, Sister Therese 1969-1973 (Box 2)
    - Fava de Moraes, Dr. Flavio 1969-1977 (Box 2)
    - General 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Older files
    - Ingle correspondence 1950-1952 (Box 3)
    - Recife Trip 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Photocopying litigation (Box 3)
  - Research
    - "The Influence of Norethyrodrel on the Hypophysis" (Box 3)
    - Thyrotropic Cell of the Rat Hypophysis as studied with Peroxidase-Labeled Antibody (Box 3)
    - Identification of the Corticotropin Cell in Rat Hypophyses with Peroxidase-Labeled Antibody (Box 3)
    - The Influence of Norethyrodrel on Sialic Acid Content of the rat Hypophysis (Box 3)
    - Differentiation of Growth Hormone and Prolactin containing Aciduphils with Peroxidase labeled Antibody (Box 3)
    - Hypophyseal Changes Induced by Thyroid Deficiency and Thyroxine Administration as revealed by Immunochemical staining (Box 3)
    - Oral Contraceptives, possible dangers (Box 3)
    - Utility of Antiserums to subunits of TSH and LH for Immunochemical Staining of the rat Hypophysis (Box 3)
    - Direct Action of Synthetic Progestins on the Hypophysis (Box 3)
    - Localization of Luteinizing Hormone-Release Hormone in the Mammalian Hypothalamus (Box 3)
    - Handbook on Physiology-chapter on Pituitary, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Human Fetus, Lanman (Box 3)
    - Human Placenta (Box 3)
  - Societies
    - American Association of Anatomists (Box 3)
    - Endocrine Society (Box 3)
    - Histochemical Society (Box 3)
    - Research Club (Box 3)
    - Science Research Club (Box 3)
    - Sigma Xi (Box 3)
    - Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine (Box 3)
    - Society for the Study of Reproduction (Box 3)
  - Teaching Notes
    - Anatomy 221
      - General (Box 3)
      - Adrenal Cortex (Box 3)
      - Female Reproductive System (Box 3)
      - Male Reproductive System (Box 3)
      - Thyroid (Box 3)
      - Neurohypophysis (Box 3)
      - Adrenal Medulla (Box 3)
      - Islets of Langerhans (Box 3)
      - Neoplasia (Box 3)
      - Hormonal Regulation of Tissues (Box 3)
      - Anterior Hypophysis (Box 3)
      - Parathyroid (Box 3)
    - Anatomy 760, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Neuroanatomy (Box 3)